Over the next 90 minutes, we’ll be taking
you through this series consisting of 21 different
segments that hope to cover the basics of
computer programming, which can apply to any
and all programming languages you might want
to learn. We’ll be starting with the simplest
question of what is programming, and from
there will be working our way up as we talk
about common features of computer science
such as loops and arrays. We’ll discuss
how to read and write code, debug code you’ve
written, some strategies to help plan out
your code, and much, much more. The complete
list of topics that are going to be covered
in this lecture-style video are shown on the
screen now. Additionally, there will be time-stamps
in the description, so feel free to skip around
if you are already proficient in some areas
of computer science, or just want to know
about a specific topic we will be covering.