This includes addition, subtraction, multiplication,
and division, all of which are represented
by the symbols shown on the screen now. In
any IDE that you may install, you’ll be
able to print out the answer to simple math
problems using the print statement, which
may seem counter-intuitive because why would
you use the computer to do math when you have
a perfectly good calculator on your phone,
but you have to remember that computers are
dumb, and anything we want a computer to do
we have to build up from scratch. Basic arithmetic,
while simple, helps out in almost any program
you may write. For example, if we wanted to
build a basic calculator app, we’d need
to utilize this functionality in order to
correctly display the answer to an arithmetic
problem when our user tries to add, subtract,
multiply, or divide two numbers.