Now when we talk about dictionaries, we’re
not referencing that thick book you probably
have lying around your house which has thousands
of definitions. In computer science, dictionaries
are like arrays, in that they store multiple
values, however their values are stored very
differently. Rather than being referenced
by their position within the dictionary linearly,
each value is tied to another value that is
used to reference it, or its “key”. Because
of this, we need to throw away all conceptions
of dictionaries as a linear way of looking
at data, since in actuality it is much more
fluid and interchanging. Basically, we say
that each position in a dictionary holds a
key/value pair. When referencing a value in
a dictionary, you will use it’s unique key,
and the dictionary will tell you the value
that is tied to it. Think of it like this,
each time you add an item to your dictionary,
your computer creates a handcrafted box to
store the data, and also custom-makes a jeweled
key, one of a kind, no other like it in the
world. This way, there is only one key that
goes to the box that stores a certain bit
of information. Because each key must be unique,
reusing a key in a dictionary will result
in an error being thrown because having two
keys that are exactly the same would confuse
the computer as to what box, or bit of information,
that key leads to. However, you can store
the same value in multiple key/value pairs,
since the keys would all be different.