Java, C++, and Python. They each have their
own different benefits over one another. Java
is best at developing games and interactive
web pages, Python can act as a scripting language
for web programming as well as writing applications
and data analysis. And C++ is best for writing
applications and system programs. They all
have a variety of packages that you can import
and use to achieve the functionality you need
from them. While selecting the right general
purpose language for your big projects is
very important, for most of your programs
any one of them will work. It really comes
down to preference. Get to know each language,
and decide which one’s syntax rules you
like best and find most comfortable. If you
get to know one general purpose language really
well and enjoy programming with it, you can
apply it to just about any of the programs
you plan on writing. Personally, I tend to
use Python for most of my projects. This is
mostly not due to any functional difference
between Python and any other general purpose
language, though there are a decent amount,
but it is mainly because I find its syntax
rules most convenient and easiest to write
programs with. Overall, either you can consider
the project you plan on doing, and research
and see which language boasts the most advantages
for your purposes, or you can simply become
comfortable with a language and use it for
most of the projects you decide to write.