What does this mean? Well let’s say you
had some String function in a game and inside
of it there was an if statement where if the
player score was above a 10, you returned
a congratulatory message. This works fine
if you print the result of this function and
the player’s score is above 10. But, if
the playerScore was less than 10 then you
don’t enter the if statement and then you
don’t have something prepared to be returned
to the user and so the function is going to
throw you an error. You HAVE to have all your
paths covered which may seem simple, but if
you’re making a function with a switch statement
in it containing high amounts of cases, this
can get out of hand quickly. Something I like
to do just to make sure this doesn’t happen
is put a return statement at the bottom of
the function with a string or an integer so
unique that I’m able to tell that the code
is not running properly and can fix it. The
main point I’m trying to get across however,
is always cover your exits and always have
a return statement prepared for any case the
user may throw at you.