It is extremely important that the base case
is set to some requirement that n will eventually
meet for the same reason that it is important
to avoid infinite loop: we do not want a stack
overflow error to occur. For example, if our
base case was to stop calling the recursive
function when n was greater than 100, and
if it is not, we call the function again but
with n-1, and we started with n as 99, we
would never reach the base case and the recursive
function will repeatedly call itself over
and over and over again, subtracting 1 from
n and hoping that somehow it will eventually
be greater than 100 until your computer crashes,
not fun. So anyways back to our recursive
sum example, let’s make our base case when
n is less than or equal to 1. This way, we
can start at some positive integer n
and subtract from it until it hits at or equal
1, in which case we can exit the recursive
statement. Cool. Now, if n is not less than
or equal to 1, what we want to do is return
the SUM of both n and then the returning value
of our recursiveSum method minus 1. Why do
we add n + the function call? Well let’s
actually go through the function as if we
were the computer and see why. We start with
a call of recursiveSum with n = 3. We know
that 3 is not less than or equal to 1 so now
we try to return a recursive sum of n (which
is 3) and the returning value of recursiveSum
with an n of 2.