and so if you wanted to make a variable that
stored the player score, you’d have to find
some way to combine the words player and score,
since you can’t have the phrase “player
score” be the name of a variable. All programmers
have their own personal preference when it
comes to naming variables, but the one we
will be using on this lecture is called CamelCase,
which is the process of not capitalizing the
first word, but capitalizing every word that
follows it. Going back to the player score
example, using the camelCase method, the variable
would be called playerScore. This allows us
to easily identify each word and becomes really
useful for long variable names like thePlayersScoreBeforeFinalBoss”,
whereas if we just type it out without capitalization,
it would be really confusing. This will help
a ton when you start to find bugs in your
code and need to quickly scan your program
to figure out whats wrong, and adds to the
overall readability of the program. Other
programmers might use different naming conventions
like using underscores to separate the words
in a phrase, but for now we’ll be sticking
with camelCase.