Imagine this, for example: you want your less-than-intelligent
friend to build a lego set, except he has
lost the instructions and can only build based
on your command. Remember though, your friend
is far from competent, and so If they are
not given very specific instructions on how
to build the set, there are many mistakes
he could make. If he thinks like a computer,
then if there is even one piece that you have
not told him specifically where to place and
how to place it, the entire lego set will
be ruined and he will be left to suffer a
complete mental breakdown causing the whole
goal of the project to be corrupted. Giving
instructions to your friend is very similar
to how programmers code. Instead of a less-than-intelligent
friend, you have a less-than-intelligent computer,
and instead of instructions on how to build
a lego set, we are feeding it information
on how to complete a program like a game or
web application. An important thing to note
is that comptuers are actually very dumb.