to update your age. All you have to do is
reference the variable, and set it equal to
whatever new integer you want the variable
to hold, in this case 18. This would be the
same as having a box labeled age, with a sheet
of paper reading 17 inside of it, and then
taking that piece of paper out, erasing 17,
replacing it with 18, and then placing it
back into the box. Doing this, we are able
to easily update the contents of our variables
throughout the code as things dynamically
shift. As another example, if you were making
an RPG, your character will likely have stats
such as attack, defense, mana, etc. As the
game progressed you could continuously update
the variables so that the player could get
more powerful the further along that they
went through the game, and you wouldn’t
have to create new variables. You would just
simply need to keep grabbing that box from
your storage facility, erasing and replacing
the numbers on the piece of paper, and then
continue along with your code. Just keep in
mind that these variables are nothing more
than places in memory in which a certain value
is stored, so we can easily update the numbers,
and their place will remain constant. After
a code has run its course, the place in memory
is deleted until you run the code again and
the program dedicates space for the variable
again. Each time you run the code, you're
making new boxes in your storage facility,
and at the end of your code, you destroy them
all to make room for new boxes next time.