to do into machine code is extremely difficult,
in fact almost impossible, and would take
a very long time to do if you could. Each
program is composed of millions upon millions
of those 1’s and 0’s, so how, exactly,
are we supposed to translate our instructions
into machine code?
This is where programming languages come into
play. Programming languages are fundamentally
a middle man for translating a program into
machine code. These languages are much easier
for humans to learn than machine code, and
are thus very useful for programmers. Going
back to our lego example, a programming language
would be sort of like an interpreter, that’s
able to take the instructions you give them
in english, and translate them into instructions
your non-english speaking friend can understand.