Alright, so in general for making functions,
each language differentiates how you tell
the computer that it's a function. In java
you have to define the functions scope, which
is something you don’t really need to know
unless you’re going to become more invested
in java, but basically it tells the computer
which parts of code can use the function and
which type can’t. For this series all of
our functions are going to be public. From
there you then determine which type of function
it is, so in this case since it won’t be
returning any variables we’ll just put void
to signify this type of function will not
be returning anything. Finally, you put the
function name after those two identifiers
along with a set of parentheses after it like
so. The parenthesis are where your arguments
would go if you were making a function that
took in arguments, but since for our first
type of function we’re not incorporating
arguments into this function, let's just leave
that blank. All of that is just for Java;
Python on the other hand all you do is put
def, short for define, and then the function
name with a set of parenthesis. So as you
can see, each language is going to be different,
but the main thing we want to remember is
to always add parentheses. From there, we
just type what we want our void function to
do within the confines of the function and
then close off the loop and we’re done,
easy peasy. In Java, the confines of the loop
would be whatever is contained within the
curly brackets, and in python it would be
until you are no longer indented. At its core,
this is the most primitive type of function
we’ve just made. Something which takes in
no arguments and returns no values, quite
similar to the printStats function from earlier
on.