This is essentially what happens with the
computer, for example, the max function which
takes two integers as arguments and returns
the maximum number between the two. Now, for
this function if you don’t input two numbers
or variables for it to compare, it's going
to throw you an error just like the five guys
employee, he doesn’t know what you want
to eat since you didn’t provide him any
arguments, and the computer doesn’t know
what two numbers you want it to compare and
return since you didn’t provide it with
two integers. Arguments are a way for programmers
to have one function that can do many different
things depending on whichever variables can
be passed through. Arguments add variability
to programming and can help diversify your
code. Thinking back to our five guys example,
a restaurant that only allows one type of
food to be made regardless of what you order
isn’t going to be very useful or diversified,
but if we’re able to pass in arguments and
tell them what food we want, our experience
can be heightened and more options become
available, which is exactly what happens when
you accept arguments in your functions.