Now before we jump into different types of
searching algorithms, we must discern between
the two states that arrays or lists can be
in, either sorted or unsorted. A sorted list
of information is characterized by some sort
of rankable value, whether that be a patient
ID, credit card number, or even by alphabetical
values like username’s or legal names. An
unsorted list is just some random assortment
of related information, not sorted by any
particular order or reason. Some searching
algorithms only work for sorted lists, usually
the more efficient ones, and some work for
both sorted and unsorted lists, although these
are usually less efficient. If you end up
pursuing computer science further, you will
have to deal with both sorted and unsorted
lists, so it's good to know common searching
practices for both
Another thing to note is that we determine
the efficiency of a searching algorithm based
on both the worst case scenario and the average
number of items it must search. We call this
Big O notation, in which each searching algorithm
has an equation which takes in the size of
the array as an integer n, and will output
an worst-case scenario efficiency value that
we can use to compare with other searching
algorithms. We can then also look at how long;
on average, it takes to find an element in
a list. Using these two methods allows us
to easily compare how efficient two algorithms
are. Alright, now that we’ve got some background
on searching, let’s hop right into it.