If not, you move on to the next name on the
list until either you find your name, or you
don’t in which case you leave. A linear
search works the same way, you start with
the first element in the list, compare it
to the value that you’re trying to find,
and if they’re the same you’ve found your
match and return the index of that element,
and if not you move on to the next element
in the list until you either find the thing
you’re searching for or you run out of list
to check. Seems pretty simple right? This
is because linear searches are pretty bad
when it comes to efficiency, especially in
the worst case scenario. If the item you’re
searching for in the list is the last element,
you’re going to have to check the entire
list of items before you find the one you’re
searching for. On average; however, you’re
going to get it about halfway through the
list. This makes the linear search O(n) worst-case
scenario, since in the worst possible case
it will take the entire length of the array,
or n, to find the correct value. The linear
search on average will return the correct
index in O(n/2) or halfway through the list.