Just a quick aside, since there is no “true”
middle, the computer automatically uses the
next one down as the “middle” value. Now,
once you find your middle value, you first
check to see if the name you’re searching
for at the index you’ve chosen, if it is
you simply return that index, but 99.9% of
the time it’s not including right now, so
let’s keep going. If the value at the middle
index is NOT equal to the one you’re searching
for, you check to see if the value you’re
searching comes before or after the middle
index. For example, if you were looking for
the name Brendan and the value at the middle
index was Carl; Brendan obviously comes before
matthew alphabetically and since we know the
list is sorted, what we can do now is ignore
the entire bottom half of the list and just
focus on the top, since we know that if Brendan
is even in the list, it’s going to be in
that top half. Now, we simply treat the top
half of the list as an entirely new entity
and repeat the process over again. Again,
we would find the middle-most element of this
new list of names and again compare it to
the name you’re trying to find. If it’s
the name we’re trying to find, we return
that index, but if not we compare to see if
it comes before or after the middle index.