Now the thing you have to understand is that
when you’re making your own functions, which
is something we will be covering soon, you
have to choose what your function will return,
if anything at all. Functions are able to
return values back to the user whether they
be String variables, integer variables, or
even arrays. Now the thing to note about returning
values is that calling the function alone
won’t do anything. You have to return the
value into something. As an example, the Max
function we talked about previously would
return an integer, but in order to do something
with it we would have to either set a new
integer variable equal to the result of that
Max function, or we can print out the result
of a function, which in this case would just
print out the maximum value between the two
integers. Using functions which return values
don’t do much on their own, you have to
pair it with something in order to gain use
out of it.