Earlier, we mentioned how you have to be careful
to set an appropriate size of your array and
make sure to only reference and append values
such that you remain within the size of the
array. However, with array lists, this isn’t
a problem. After you initialize an arrayList,
it instinctively has a size of 10, but if
you append a values such that the size of
the arrayList goes beyond 10 elements, an
arrayList will “grow” itself, meaning
that the computer will allocate more memory
to the array to increase its total size so
that the new values can be appended. This
is quite useful when you don’t know the
exact number of values that the array will
need to store, or want the ability to store
values to your heart’s content, such as
making a database with an unknown amount of
user’s that will sign up.