Starting with the biggest question which is
what’s the next step. Well, now that you
might know which type of language you might
be interested in, research that language and
find out whether or not you truly want to
pursue that programming language. Most languages
like python or C++ will have either an official
website where you can read up on, or a wikipedia
page which will provide you with useful information
in deciding whether or not you want to pursue
that path. From there, the next step is to
actually learn the language, which can be
done right here on YouTube. While we have
taught you the basics of any programming language,
each specific language is going to expand
upon the basic concepts and so watching tutorial
videos on a certain language is going to be
very beneficial. Many websites will try to
get you to purchase paid courses or take classes
which cost money, but you can find extremely
good courses here on YouTube for absolutely
0 cost to yourself. I would start with an
introduction series like the one you’re
currently watching, but for the language you
have chosen and work your way through that
series, picking up on the syntax and rules
of that language until you become comfortable
with it.