statements and functions you want to use,
just jot down, from start to finish, what
it is the program you are writing is going
to do step by step. For example, let’s say
you’re making an app that takes in two numbers
and divides them. The pseudocode for that
would look a little something like this. First
I want to prompt the user to enter a number,
then I want to wait for the user to input
the first number. After I get the first number,
I want to again prompt the user to input a
second number. Once they do, I complete the
operation by dividing the two numbers entered
and return the result back to the user. This
all seems like it would be common sense, but
remember that oftentimes we’re not going
to be working with simple multiplication functions,
we may be working with full-scale games, algorithms,
or user interfaces with many different options.