Now, programming languages allow us to do
some pretty cool things with these “boxes”
that we’ve created. For example, let’s
say we created a second variable “channelName”
and instead of setting it equal to “NullPointerException”,
we instead set it equal to our already created
“Name” variable. This doesn’t create
a space in memory for this new variable; however,
it simply points to the same location of memory
we have already created for the “Name”
variable. Going back to our storage facility
example, this would like if instead of creating
a whole new box labeled “channelName”
and storing a sheet of paper with the word
“NullPointerException” on it, we instead
simply added another label below the “Name”
box, entitled “channelName”. Now, we have
two variables but both point towards the same
contents, that being the string “NullPointerException”.