not be read by the program as code, and will
be skipped over. Essentially, it becomes something
that is only there for YOU the programmer
to read. The syntax varies from language to
language, but it usually involves placing
some symbols before or around the code you
would like to be commented. Examples of how
to comment in different languages can be seen
on the screen now. Also, when you comment
something, the IDE will grayscale the line
of code, making it extremely easy to determine
what’s commented and what is not. Commenting
code ‘deletes’ it in the computer’s
eyes without actually deleting it. If a problem
is present before you comment a section of
code but it is gone afterward, then that section
of code is the culprit. If you comment part
of a code out and there are still issues,
then move onto another section until you find
the culprit. Once you do, you can tweak it
until it works as intended or delete it entirely
and you will have a fully functioning program
once again. Hurrah!
Now that we’ve talked about what to do IF
you’ve encountered an error and a strategy
on how to find and fix it, I’d like to talk
about some strategies you can use to AVOID
errors in the first place. Firstly, backup
your code frequently. In the event of the
code completely bugging out and you being
unable to fix it, you will want the ability
to revert to a previous version where the
code was still working. If you save frequently
enough, then you will probably not lose too
much work. Version managers like Github or
Subversion can help with this, as they backup
code to an online cloud service in which you
can easily pull previous versions of the program
at any point.