Now, whenever we want to call the multiplyNumbers
function, we just have to make sure that we
are putting 2 numbers in as arguments. In
this case the number 5 becomes num1, and the
number 8 becomes num2. From there we simply
run the code and the number 40 is printed
to the console. It’s important to note that
you can also mix and match variables when
making arguments. So you can have someFunction
which takes in a char, an integer, and two
strings all within one function. Pretty neat
in my opinion. The last thing I want to mention
about arguments is that when you call a function
you have to follow the variables you defined
when making the function. So for our multiplyNumbers
function you couldn’t put in a string and
then an int. It HAS to be two integers because
that’s what the computer is expecting to
be passed into the function.