instead of putting in the Office, you put
in FRIENDS on blu ray. No michael, no inappropriate
joke, meaning your friend would be sitting
there for the rest of his life probably confused
as to why Dunder Mifflin looks so much like
a coffee shop. This is essentially what happens
with the computer, you give it some condition
that it has to complete before the program
can terminate; however, you give it no feasible
way to finish that task. This puts the computer
in error mode and most likely will crash your
program, as the computer desperately tries
to complete the condition you gave it. As
a computer example, if we try to have a program
terminate when an integer i is no longer greater
than 99, but i is initially 100 and only increases,
the loop will never terminate and the program
will crash. To avoid these, you generally
want to think through the flow of your code
before running it -especially with loops-
to make sure that all of your statements can
be completed by the computer. Carefully planning
out your code before you begin writing it
is an extremely useful practice, and something
we’ll be covering towards the later part
of this video.