So at this point we’ve talked about both
what functions are and how we can get some
very useful functions by importing functions
through packages. But there are definitely
going to be moments in your programming journey
where you’re going to want to make your
own functions because you want to make one
specific to your program and code. Luckily,
making your own functions is extremely simple,
there are just some basic rules I want to
cover. Now while we’ve previously used making
functions as an example for other topics such
as the playerStats function from a little
bit ago, they were extremely abstract and
didn’t go in depth into what is needed for
an actual function to operate. So right now
we’re going to be covering a skeletal system
of everything that needs to be included in
a function to get it to work.