This can be anything, from forgetting a semicolon
at the end of a statement in java, accidentally
defining a variable with two words instead
of one, or even just misspelling the word
String when you’re trying to define a string
variable. Lucky for you guys, these errors
are extremely easy to fix since you just need
to figure out where the error occurred and
what the syntax rule you broke was. Now thinking
back to IDE’s, we mentioned that IDE’s
are so useful because they do precisely that,
they underline syntax errors and usually provide
helpful hints as to how to fix them. Think
of syntax errors as small misspellings or
grammatical errors in an essay you’re writing,
annoying; yes, but not the most infuriating
things. Another useful thing about IDE’s
when it comes to syntax errors is that the
program will actually restrict you from running
the code unless all syntax errors are cleared,
making them even easier to identify and fix.