When you initialize an array, you give it
a size, and this size is fixed. You won’t
be able to increase the size of the array,
so when you make an array, it’s length is
final. To access the values in an array, you
reference them using an index which starts
at 0. What this means is that the first item
of an array is not at position 1, it is at
position 0, and it’s position is commonly
referred to as it’s index location. So,
to find the nth item in an array, you would
refer to it as index location [n-1]. However,
as the size of an array is fixed, you have
to be careful to not reference a position
that is beyond the total size of the array,
or append too many items to it, as this will
return an error. We also have what are known
as two-dimensional arrays,
which is an array containing an array at each
of its indexes. Or, you could have an array
containing arrays containing arrays containing
arrays containing arrays, depending one what
you’re trying to do. Multidimensional arrays
can be useful in more advanced programs for
organizing a wide volume of related values.