Another cool thing you can do with variables
is add them, subtract them, multiply them,
divide them, and even modulus them. Now this
mostly only works for integer variables as
multiplying and dividing strings doesn’t
make too much sense. But if you were making
a calculator app and you stored the first
number the user entered as num1, and the second
as num2. You could then multiply num1 and
num2 together, and either print them, or store
them in a new variable entitled result. Then,
each time you run the program, the user could
input new numbers into the num1 and num2 variables,
and they would simply be set to those new
integers and return the result that corresponds
to those specific numbers. This allows for
you to keep easy track of which numbers are
which and what’s going on in your program
which is extremely useful. Also, while you
cannot subtract, multiply, divide, or take
the modulus of strings, you are able to add
them. Let’s say you had a string Str1 with
the contents “Hello “ and a Str2 with
the contents “there”. You could add Str1
and Str2 to create a string that had the contents
“Hello there”, either storing it in a
third variable or printing it out to the console.