middle index of this new list is AJ. Now,
we know that Brendan comes AFTER AJ alphabetically
so we can now ignore the top half of the list
since we know that Brendan is going to be
in the top of our list. Now we repeat this
process again and again until we find the
name we are looking for. So for our example,
the middle index this time is Brendan, and
that’s what we’re searching for so we
finally would return index 2. In binary search,
eventually the index we compare to our search
term will be the same and once it is, we can
return the index and move on. Now if we don’t
find it, which happens after we have eliminated
the entirety of the list without finding our
search term, the algorithm will simply return
a null value to let you know that the item
you’re searching for cannot be found in
the list. The binary search is way faster
and more efficient than the linear search
since we are drastically cutting down the
amount of elements we have to look at, making
the program run faster. In almost 99.9% of
cases in which your list is sorted, the binary
search is going to return a result faster
than the linear search, so if you have a sorted
list, your best option is to go binary. As
for efficiency, the binary search is O(log
n) for the worst case scenario which can be
confusing if you don’t fully understand
logarithms, but all you need to know is that
it is way more efficient than the linear search.